Guide to the Rachel Carson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- General Correspondence, 1942-73; Series II; 2.5; (5 boxes)
  - Spock, Marjorie, 1958-64 (Box 105, Folder 2006-08)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1956-57 (Box 105, Folder 2009)
  - "T" general, 1952-61 (Box 106, Folder 2010)
  - Teale, Edwin Way, 1951-64 (Box 106, Folder 2011)
    See also: Box 86, folder 1514
  - "U" general, 1951 (Box 106, Folder 2012)
  - United States Department of the Interior, 1952-60 (Box 106, Folder 2013)
  - "V" general, 1952-63 (Box 106, Folder 2014)
  - Vishniac, Roman, 1954-55 (Box 106, Folder 2015)
  - "W" general, 1945-62 (Box 106, Folder 2016)
  - Wilson, Douglas P., 1955-56 (Box 106, Folder 2017)
  - Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute, 1952-56 (Box 106, Folder 2018)
    See also: Harvey, E. Newton, Box 103, folder 1953
  - "X-Y-Z" general, 1953, n.d. (Box 106, Folder 2019)
  - Unidentified, 1941-53 (Box 106, Folder 2020-21)
  - Requests
    - Contributions to magazines, 1954-64 (Box 106, Folder 2022-23)
    - Information, 1955-64 (Box 106, Folder 2024-25)
    - Reprints and quotations, 1942-63 (Box 106, Folder 2026-28)
    - Speaking engagements, 1951-64 (Box 106, Folder 2029-35)
  - Manuscript disposition, 1954-64 (Box 106, Folder 2036)
    See also: Box 108
  - Fan mail (General), n.d. (Box 106, Folder 2037-39)
- Personal Papers, 1937-89; Series III; 3; (7 boxes)
  Series III, Personal Papers, consists of typescripts,
  notes, newspaper articles, photos, and printed works
  related to Carson's career and life, arranged
  alphabetically by subject.
  - Appearances and lectures: notices (Box 107, Folder 2040)
  - Awards and Honors
    - AAAS-Westinghouse: Science Writing Award, 1950 (Box 107, Folder 2041)
    - American Geographical Society: Cullum Geographical Medal, 1963-64 (Box 107, Folder 2042)
      See also: Box 99, folder 1835
    - Drexel Institute: Distinguished Achievement Award, 1963 (Box 107, Folder 2043)
      See also: Box 99, folder 1855
    - Garden Club of America: Frances K. Hutchinson Medal, 1952 (Box 107, Folder 2044)
    - Geographical Society of Philadelphia, 1952 (Box 107, Folder 2045)
    - New England Outdoor Writers' Association: Distinguished Service Award, 1963 (Box 107, Folder 2046)
    - Roosevelt University. Women's Scholarship Committee: Leadership for Freedom Award, 1962 (Box 107, Folder 2047)
    - "Who's Who of American Women": citation, 1963, n.d. (Box 107, Folder 2048)
    - Other awards and honors, 1951-63 (Box 107, Folder 2049-54)
    - Posthumous awards, 1964 (Box 107, Folder 2055)
    - Honorary degrees, 1951-64 (Box 107, Folder 2056-57)
    - Honorary memberships, 1951-63 (Box 107, Folder 2058-59)
  - Bequests, 1964 (Box 108, Folder 2060)
  - Biographical information
    - Profiles, 1962-64, n.d. (Box 108, Folder 2061-62)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1951-64, n.d. (Box 108, Folder 2063-64)
    - Barnes, Irston. "Rachel Carson at Work": typescript, 1972 Mar 26 (Box 108, Folder 2065)
    - Brooks, Paul. "Rachel Carson." Book-of-the-Month Club News: typescript and printed copy, [1962] (Box 108, Folder 2066)
    - Brooks, Paul. Biographical material for The House of Life, 1954-71 (Box 108, Folder 2067)
    - Doss, Margaret. "Long Time No Sea", n.d. (Box 108, Folder 2068)
    - Ford, Anne. Untitled biographical sketch, n.d. (Box 108, Folder 2069)
    - Free, Anne Cottrell. "Quiet Fighter." Louisville Courier-Journal, 1963 Feb 3 (Box 108, Folder 2070)
    - Gavagan, James E. Untitled sketch for New York State Conservationist: galley proofs (corrected by Rachel Carson?), 1962 (Box 108, Folder 2071)
    - Halle, Louis J. "Recollections of Rachel Carson": typescript, n.d. (Box 108, Folder 2072)
    - "Rachel Carson and Silent Spring." Chatham Alumnae Recorder, 1962 Fall (Box 108, Folder 2073)
    - Setzer, Dorothy. "Problems Piscatorial." Cotuit-on-Cape Cod Current, 1952 Aug 28 (Box 108, Folder 2074)
    - Thorpe, W. H. "Tribute to Rachel Carson." Mother Earth (Can.): photocopy, n.d. (Box 108, Folder 2075)
    - Yuncker, Barbara. "A Voice Amid the Silence." New York Post, 1962 Sep 30 (Box 108, Folder 2076)
    - Autobiographical sketches, 1944-58 (Box 108, Folder 2077)
    - Letters with biographical content, 1964, 1971 (Box 108, Folder 2078)
  - Condolences (letters to Marie Rodell on Rachel Carson's death), 1964 (Box 108, Folder 2079)
  - Notes and notebooks (Box 108, Folder 2080-86)
  - Obituaries, 1964 (Box 109, Folder 2087-91)
  - Photographs
    - Carson family, [ca. 1910] (Box 109, Folder 2092)
    - Rachel Carson, 1962, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2093-98)
      See also: Box 107, folder 2056
    - Louis and Lois Darling, 1968 (Box 109, Folder 2099)
    - Robert Hines, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2100)
    - Edwin and Nellie Teal (and cats) (Box 109, Folder 2101)
    - Negatives, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2102)
    - Newspaper, magazine photos, 1952, 1963, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2103)
  - Printed material
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters: ceremonial program, 1953 May 27 (Box 109, Folder 2104)
    - Bernstein, Joseph. "Tsunamis", n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2105)
    - Briejèr, C. J. "Een Kritische Beschouwing over Het Gebruik van Insekten en Andere Ongewenste Organismen", [1966] (Box 109, Folder 2106)
    - Brooks, Paul. "Alaska: The Last Frontier." Atlantic Monthly, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2107)
    - Brooks, Paul. "The Great Smokies." Atlantic Monthly, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2108)
    - Cassell, Richard L. "Fannie Was a Bat." Nature Magazine, 1944 Nov (Box 109, Folder 2109)
    - Crisler, Lois. "Captive Wild": typescript, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2110)
    - Darling, Lois. "Commentary", 1983 Mar 17 (Box 109, Folder 2111)
    - Ellis, H. P. "Please Leave the Sea As You Would Like to Find It." Punch, 1953 Jul 6 (Box 109, Folder 2112)
    - Enoch, Kurt. The Paper-Bound Book, 1954 Jul (Box 109, Folder 2113)
    - Frome, Michael. "Let's Rescue Our Roadsides--Now." American Forests, 1963 Nov (Box 109, Folder 2114)
    - George, John L. "The Work of the IUCN's Committee", 1966 (Box 109, Folder 2115)
    - Greenbaum, Maurice C. "The Professional Writer", 1957 (Box 109, Folder 2116)
    - Hedgpath, Joel W. "An Introduction to the Zoogeography of the Northwestern Gulf of Mexico with Reference to the Invertebrate Fauna" (Reprint), 1953 (Box 109, Folder 2117)
    - Henry, Thomas R. "Vistas in Science": newspaper series, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2118)
    - Humane Treatment of Animals Used in Research Hearings...Eighty-Seventh Congress, 1962 (Box 109, Folder 2119)
    - Kelly, Walt. Pogo Primer for Parents, 1961 (Box 109, Folder 2120)
    - McMillen, Wheeler. Bugs or People?, n.d. (Box 109, Folder 2121)
    - Murie, Olaus J. "Wild Country as a National Asset." The Living Wilderness, 1953 Summer (Box 110, Folder 2122)
    - New Jersey State Agricultural Experiment Station (Department of Biology): yearly reports, 1925-28 (Box 110, Folder 2123)
    - Nigrelli, Ross and Paul A. Zahl. "Some Biological Characteristics of Holothurin." (Reprint), 1952 (Box 110, Folder 2124)
    - Oceanography in the United States. Hearings...Eighty-Sixth Congress, 1959 (Box 110, Folder 2125)
    - Pearse, A. S., H. J. Humm, and G. W. Wharton, "Ecology of Sand Beaches of Beaufort, N. C." Ecological Monographs, 1942 Apr (Box 110, Folder 2126)
    - Peet, Creighton. "Yes, Tall Oaks from Little Acorns Grow." American Forests, 1963 Oct (Box 110, Folder 2127)
    - Report on the Committee on Paleoecology, 1936-37 (Annual meeting of the Division of Geology and Geography, National Research Council) (Reprint), 1937 May 1 (Box 110, Folder 2128)
    - Richards, Horace G. "Geology of the Coastal Plain of North Carolina." (Transactions of the American Philosophical Society), 1950 Aug (Box 110, Folder 2129)
    - Riddick, Thomas. "The Bends and Other Causes of Death in Aquarium Fish" (Box 110, Folder 2130)
    - Rorty, James. "Food or Famine" (Reprinted from Commentary ): typescript, n.d. (Box 110, Folder 2131)
    - Rorty, James. "Hunger Is Obsolete, If--", n.d. (Box 110, Folder 2132)
    - Rorty, James. "TVA's H. A. Morgan", n.d. (Box 110, Folder 2133)
    - Starr, John T. "Where the Forest Meets the Sea." American Forests: photocopy, 1963 Nov (Box 110, Folder 2134)
    - Stephenson, T. A. and Anne Stevenson. Life Between the Tide-Marks in North America: I. The Florida Keys, II. Northern Florida and the Carolinas, III. Nova Scotia and Prince Edward Island, 1950-54 (Box 110, Folder 2135)
    - Theta Sigma Phi brochures, n.d. (Box 110, Folder 2136)
    - Transatlantic, 1945 Apr (Box 110, Folder 2137)
    - Trecker, Jan. "The Interrelatedness of It All" [on Lois Darling]. The Gazette, 1983 Feb 10 (Box 110, Folder 2138)
    - Van Fleet, Clark C. "Silent Spring on the Pacific Slope: A Postscript to Rachel Carson." The Atlantic Monthly, n.d. (Box 110, Folder 2139)
    - Voyages (Program). The English Theatre Company of Norway, [1965] (Box 110, Folder 2140)
    - Waterman, Talbot H.
      - "Flight Instruments in Insects." American Scientific (Reprint), 1950 Spring (Box 110, Folder 2141)
      - "Polarized Flight Navigation by Anthropods." Transactions of the New York Academy of Science (Reprint), 1951 Nov (Box 110, Folder 2141)
    - Wadsworth, Virginia Ewarts. "Rachel Carson: Protector of Planet Earth." Cobblestone, 1989 August (Box 110, Folder 2142)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper articles, 1968-69 (Box 110, Folder 2143)
  - Rejection slips, 1928, n.d. (Box 110, Folder 2144)
  - Subject files
    - Agricultural Publications lists, 1962-63, n.d. (Box 110, Folder 2145-46)
    - Annelids, 1941-52 (Box 110, Folder 2147)
    - Assateague Island Conservation, 1963 (Box 111, Folder 2148)
    - Bacteria, 1943-50 (Box 111, Folder 2149)
    - Coelenterates, 1939, 1951 (Box 111, Folder 2150)
    - Commensalism, 1950-51 (Box 111, Folder 2151)
    - Conservation (Stevenson Committee), 1956 (Box 111, Folder 2152)
    - Crustaceans, 1912-45 (Box 111, Folder 2153)
    - Echinoderms, 1933 (Box 111, Folder 2154)
    - Horseshoe crabs, 1950-53, n.d. (Box 111, Folder 2155)
    - Indiana Dunes National Lakeshore Conservation Project, 1962-63 (Box 111, Folder 2156)
    - Mollusks, 1948-54 (Box 111, Folder 2157)
    - Oceanographic studies, 1951-63 (Box 111, Folder 2158-62)
    - Padre Island National Seashore, 1962 (Box 111, Folder 2163)
    - Science (general), 1962, n.d. (Box 111, Folder 2164)
    - Shellfish, 1950-52 (Box 111, Folder 2165)
    - Sponges, 1947, 1953 (Box 111, Folder 2166)
    - Turtles, 1949 Aug (Box 112, Folder 2167)
    - Wildlife booklets list, n.d. (Box 112, Folder 2168)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1931-63, n.d. (Box 112, Folder 2169-71)
  - Tributes
    - Clippings, 1963-64 (Box 112, Folder 2172-79)
    - Briggs, Shirley. "Rachel Carson." Atlantic Naturalist, 1964 Apr-Jun (Box 112, Folder 2180)
    - Briggs, Shirley. "The Rachel Carson National Wildlife Refuge.", 1970 (Box 112, Folder 2181)
    - Brooks, Paul. "The National Wildlife Federation's Conservation Hall of Fame." National Wildlife, 1972 Feb-Mar (Box 112, Folder 2182)
    - Brooks, Paul. "Rachel Carson." Nature Conservancy News, 1964 Summer (Box 112, Folder 2183)
    - "A Buddhist Tribute to Rachel Carson", 1964 (Box 112, Folder 2184)
    - Free, Ann Cottrell. "The Great Awakening", 1969 Apr (Box 112, Folder 2185)
    - Free, Ann Cottrell. "Rachel Carson, 1907-1964." Defenders of Wildlife News Bulletin, 1964 May (Box 112, Folder 2186)
    - Rachel Carson commemorative stamp, 1981 (Box 112, Folder 2187)
    - Rachel Carson Wildlife Refuge: Dedication News Release, 1970 (Box 112, Folder 2188)
    - Spock, Marjorie and Mary T. Richards. "Portrait of Rachel", 1966 (Box 113, Folder 2189)
    - Udall, Stewart. "The Legacy of Rachel Carson." Saturday Review, 1964 May 16 (Box 113, Folder 2190)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1951-70 (Box 113, Folder 2191-2202)
- Oversize, 1958-65; 4; (4 boxes)
  - Under the Sea-Wind: scrapbook (Box 114, Folder 2203)
  - The Sea Around Us: scrapbook (Box 114, Folder 2204)
  - The Sea Around Us (Young Readers' Edition): layout proofs (Box 115, Folder 2205)
  - The Sea Around Us (Young Readers' Edition): galley proofs (Box 115, Folder 2206)
  - Scrapbook ( Silent Spring and pesticide issues) (Box 116, Folder 2207)
  - Silent Spring: page proofs ("Proof of Editorial or Makeup"), 1962 (Box 117, Folder 2208-10)
  - "La Natura Avvelenata." L'Europeo, 1963 May 26 (Box 117, Folder 2211)
  - "La Morte Invisible." L'Europeo, 1963 Jun 2 (Box 117, Folder 2212)
  - "Help Your Child to Wonder." Woman's Home Companion, 1956 Jul (Box 117, Folder 2213)
  - "The Sense of Wonder." McCall's, 1965 Jun (Box 117, Folder 2214)
  - The Sense of Wonder (ABC-TV adaptation): publicity poster (Box 117, Folder 2215)
  - The Sense of Wonder: scrapbook (Box 117, Folder 2216)
  - "Our Ever-Changing Shore." Holiday, 1958 Jul (Box 117, Folder 2217)
  - Silent Spring: illustrations, n.d. (Box 118, Folder 2218-19)
  - The Sense of Wonder: page proofs, 1965 (Box 118, Folder 2219a)
  - "The Silent Spring of Rachel Carson", CBS Reports film, 1963 Apr 3 (Box 119, Folder 2220-21)
- Restricted Fragile, 1; (2 cold storage items)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 119, folder 2220 (Box CS, Folder 2222)
  - Box 119, folder 2221 (Box CS, Folder 2223)